Today, I'd like to talk with you
اليوم , انا اريد التحدث معكم
about something that should be a totally uncontroversial topic.
عن شئ يجب الا يكون هناك خلف عليه ابدا
But, unfortunately, it's become incredibly controversial.
ولكن , مع الاسف انه اصبح مثير للجدل بشكل لا يصدق
This year, if you think about it,
هذه السنه , لو فكرت فيه ,
over a billion couples will have sex with one another.
اكثر من مليار زوج سيمارسون الجنس مع بعضهم .
Couples like this one,
ازواج مثل هؤلاء,
and this one,
وهؤلاء ,
and, yes,
و , نعم
even this one.
حتي هذا النوع
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And my idea is this --
وفكرتي هي --
all these men and women should be free to decide
كل هذه الرجال والنساء يجيب ان يكونوا احرار للاختيار
whether they do or do not want to conceive a child.
سواء كانوا يريدوا انجاب اطفال او لا
And they should be able to use one of these birth control methods
و يجب ان يكونو قادرين علي استخدام واحد من موانع الحمل هذه
to act on their decision.
للعمل علي قرارهم .
Now, I think you'd have a hard time
الان , اعتقد انكم ستحظوا بوقت صعب
finding many people who disagree with this idea.
لايجاد العديد من الناس الذين لا يوافقون هذه الفكره .
Over one billion people use birth control without any hesitation at all.
اكثر من مليار شخص يستخدمون موانع الحمل بدون ادني تردد.
They want the power to plan their own lives
انهم يحتاجون قوة ليخططوا لحياتهم
and to raise healthier, better educated and more prosperous families.
ورفع مستوي صحتهم , ويتعلموا احسن وان يصبحوا اسر اكثر ازدهارا.
But, for an idea that is so broadly accepted in private,
ولكن , تقبل هذه الفكرة علي نطاق واسع في المستوي الشخصي ,
birth control certainly generates a lot of opposition in public.
منع الحمل بالتاكيد يولد المعارضه في الاماكن العامه.
Some people think when we talk about contraception
بعض الناس تعتقد عندما نتحدث عن موانع الحمل
that it's code for abortion,
انه رمز للاجهاض ,
which it's not.
ولكنه ليس اجهاض .
Some people -- let's be honest --
بعض الناس -- لنكن صادقين --
they're uncomfortable with the topic because it's about sex.
انهم غير مستريحين مع هذا المجال لانه عن الجنس .
Some people worry
بعض الناس لا تهتم
that the real goal of family planning is to control populations.
هذا هو الهدف من تنظيم الاسره انه يتحكم في عدد السكان
These are all side issues
وهذه كلها قضايا جانبيه
that have attached themselves to this core idea that men and women
و ترفق نفسها لهذه الفكرة الاساسيه يجب علي ال رجال والنساء
should be able to decide when they want to have a child.
يجب ان يكونوا قادرين علي الاختيار متي يريدون ان ينجبوا طفل
And as a result, birth control has almost completely and totally disappeared
والنتيجه , منع الحمل اختفي تقريبا
from the global health agenda.
من اجندت الصحه العالميه .
The victims of this paralysis are the people of sub-Saharan Africa
ضحايا هذا الشلل هم اهل جنوب الصحراء الكبري
and South Asia.
و اسيا الجنوبيه .
Here in Germany, the proportion of people that use contraception
هنا في المنيا ,نسبة السكان المستخدمين لوسائل منع الحمل
is about 66 percent.
تكون حوالي 66 في مائة
That's about what you'd expect.
هذا تقريبا ما كنت تتقوع
In El Salvador, very similar, 66 percent.
وفي دولة سلفادور , قريب جدا , 66 في المائة
Thailand, 64 percent.
تايلاند ,64 في المائه
But let's compare that to other places,
ولكن لنقارن هذا باماكن اخري ,
like Uttar Pradesh, one of the largest states in India.
مثل اوتار براديش واحده من اكبر الولايات في الهند .
In fact, if Uttar Pradesh was its own country,
في الحقيقه لو اوتار براديش كانت مستقله ,
it would be the fifth largest country in the world.
كانت من الممكن ان تكون خامس اكبر دولة في العالم .
Their contraception rate -- 29 percent.
معدل منع الحمل عندهم -- 29 في المائه .
Nigeria, the most populous country in Africa, 10 percent.
نيجيريا , اكبر دوله من حيث عدد السكان في افريقيا , 10 في المائه.
Chad, 2 percent.
التشاد ,2 في المائة
Let's just take one country in Africa, Senegal.
لناخذ دولة واحده في افريقيا , السنغال.
Their rate is about 12 percent.
النسبة حوالي 12 في المائة
But why is it so low?
ولكن لماذا قليله ؟
One reason is that the most popular contraceptives are rarely available.
سبب واحد هو الاكثر شيوعا وسائل منع الحمل نادرا ما تتوافر.
Women in Africa will tell you over and over again
المرأه في افريقيا ستقول لك مرارا واتكرارا
that what they prefer today is an injectable.
انهم يفضلون اليوم الحقن .
They get it in their arm -- and they go about four times a year,
الذي ياخذونه في اذرعتهم -- وياخذونه حوالي 4 مرات في السنه ,
they have to get it every three months -- to get their injection.
ويجب عليهم ان يحصلوا عليه كل ثلاثة اشهر-- لياخذوا حقنهم .
The reason women like it so much in Africa is they can hide it from their husbands,
السبب الذي يشبه نساء كثير في افريقيا انهم بامكانهم الاختباء من ازواجهم ,
who sometimes want a lot of children.
الذي يريد بعضهم عدد كبير من الاطفال.
The problem is every other time a woman goes into a clinic in Senegal,
المشكله هي كل مرة تذهب فيها المراه للعياده في السنغال,
that injection is stocked out.
الحقن يكون قد نفذ
It's stocked out 150 days out of the year.
انه نافذ 150 يوم في السنه .
So can you imagine the situation --
لذلك بامكانك تخيل الحاله --
she walks all this way to go get her injection.
انها تمشي كل هذا الطريق لتحصل علي حقنها .
She leaves her field, sometimes leaves her children,
انها تترك ارضها , احيانا تترك اطفالها ,
and it's not there.
وهو ليس موجود .
And she doesn't know when it's going to be available again.
وهي ايضا لا تعليم متي سيتاح مره اخري .
This is the same story across the continent of Africa today.
هذه هي نفس القصه في جميع انحاء افريقيا اليوم .
And so what we've created as a world has become a life-and-death crisis.
وذلك ما انشئنا كعالم اصبحت مشكلة حياة او موت .
There are 100,000 women [per year] who say they don't want to be pregnant
يوجد 100.000 امرأه [سنويا] يقولون انهم لا يردون ان يصبحوا حوامل
and they die in childbirth -- 100,000 women a year.
ويموت اثناء الولاده -- 100.000 امرأه [سنويا]
There are another 600,000 women [per year]
هناك 600.000 [اخرين سنويا]
who say they didn't want to be pregnant in the first place,
يقولون انهم لا يردون ان يصبوحوا حوامل في البدايه ,
and they give birth to a baby
ويلدوا طفل
and her baby dies in that first month of life.
ثم يموت طفلهم في الشهر الاول من حياته.
I know everyone wants to save these mothers and these children.
انا اعرف ان كل شخص يريد ان يحافظ علي هذه الامهات والاطفال .
But somewhere along the way, we got confused by our own conversation.
ولكن في مكان ما طوال الطريق , حدث خلط لنا بنقاشاتنا .
And we stopped trying to save these lives.
و توقفنا لمحاولة الحفاظ علي هذه الارواح .
So if we're going to make progress on this issue,
لذلك اذا كنا في طريقنا لعمل تثدم في هذه المشكله ,
we have to be really clear about what our agenda is.
يجب ان نكون واضحين حول ما هو برنامجنا .
We're not talking about abortion.
نحن لا نتحدث عن الاجهاض .
We're not talking about population control.
نحن لا نتحدث عن تحديد النسل
What I'm talking about is giving women the power to save their lives,
ما اتحدث عنه هة اعطاء النساء القوة للحفاظ علي ارواحهم ,
to save their children's lives
وارواح اطفالهم
and to give their families the best possible future.
ولاعطاء اسرهم افضل مستقبل ممكن .
Now, as a world,
الان , كعالم
there are lots of things we have to do in the global health community
يوجد العديد من الاشيا يجب عملها في مجتمع الصحه العالمي
if we want to make the world better in the future --
لو اردنا ان نجعل العالم افضل في المستقبل --
things like fight diseases.
اشياء مثل محاربة الامراض .
So many children today die of diarrhea, as you heard earlier, and pneumonia.
يموت الان عدد كبيرمن الاطفال بسبب الاسهال, كما سمعتم سابقا ,والالتهاب الرئوي .
They kill literally millions of children a year.
انهم يقتلون ملايين الاطفال حرفيا .
We also need to help small farmers --
يجب علينا ايضا مساعدة صغار الفلاحين --
farmers who plow small plots of land in Africa --
الفلاحين الذين يحرثون قطع صغيرة من الاراضي في افريقيا --
so that they can grow enough food to feed their children.
حتي يمكن ان يزرعوا غذاء كافي لاطعام اطفالهم .
And we have to make sure that children are educated around the world.
و يجب علينا التاكد من ان الاطفال يتعلمون حول العالم .
But one of the simplest and most transformative things we can do
ولكن واحد من ابسط واكثر الامور المغيره التي ممكن ان نفعلها
is to give everybody access to birth control methods
ان نسمح لكل شخص الوصول لسبل منع الحمل
that almost all Germans have access to and all Americans, at some point,
تقريبا كل الالمان يمكنهم الوصول والامريكان , في نفس النقطه ,
they use these tools during their life.
انهم يستخدمون هذه الادوات خلال حياتهم .
And I think as long as we're really clear about what our agenda is,
وانا اظن طالما كنا واضحين حول ما هو برنامجنا ,
there's a global movement waiting to happen
هناك خطوة عالميه في انتظار ان تتخذ
and ready to get behind this totally uncontroversial idea.
ومستعده للحصول علي ما وراء هذه الفكره الغير مثيره للجدل تماما
When I grew up, I grew up in a Catholic home.
عندما كنت صغيره كنت اعيش في بيت كاثوليكي .
I still consider myself a practicing Catholic.
انا لازلت اعتبر نفسي كاثوليكيه متدينه .
My mom's great-uncle was a Jesuit priest.
عمة امي الكبري كانت قسيسه .
My great-aunt was a Dominican nun.
عمتي الكبري كانت راهبه .
She was a schoolteacher and a principal her entire life.
لقد كانت مدرسه و وهو الرئيسي في حياتها .
In fact, she's the one who taught me as a young girl how to read.
في الحقيقة , لقد كانت من علمني كفتاه صغيره كيف اقرأ
I was very close to her.
انا كنت قريبه جدا منها .
And I went to Catholic schools for my entire childhood
وذهبت للمدرسه الماثوليكيه طفولتي كلها
until I left home to go to university.
حتي تركت البيت لذهب الي الجامعه .
In my high school, Ursuline Academy,
في المدرسه الثانويه ,اكاديمية ارسيلون ,
the nuns made service and social justice a high priority in the school.
الراهبات جعلوا الخدمه المقدمه والعداله الاجتماعيه اولويه عاليه في المدرسه .
Today, in the [Gates] Foundation's work,
اليوم , في [Gates] عمل المؤسسه ,
I believe I'm applying the lessons that I learned in high school.
انا اؤمن انا اطبق الدروس التي تعلمتها من المدرسه الثاويه .
So, in the tradition of Catholic scholars,
ذلك , من تقاليد العلماء الكاثوليك ,
the nuns also taught us to question received teachings.
الراهبات ايضا قالو لنا ان نسال عن التعالسم المعطاه .
And one of the teachings that we girls and my peers questioned
واحده من التعاليم التي سالت فيها انا وزملائي
was is birth control really a sin?
هل كان منع الحمل خطئا ؟
Because I think one of the reasons
لاني فكرت في سبب واحد
we have this huge discomfort talking about contraception
لدينا هذا الحجم الكبير من الضجه حول وسائل منع الحمل
is this lingering concern
هذا الشأن الذي طال امده
that if we separate sex from reproduction, we're going to promote promiscuity.
اننا اذا فصلنا الجنس من الانجاب , نحن ندعم الدعاره .
And I think that's a reasonable question to be asked about contraception --
واعتقد انه سؤال يستحق الطرح حول موانع الحمل
what is its impact on sexual morality?
ما تأثيره علي الاخلاق الجنسيه ؟
But, like most women,
ولكن, مثل جميع النساء ,
my decision about birth control had nothing to do with promiscuity.
ولكن قراري نحو منع الحمل لم يجد شئ ليفعله مع الممارسه الغير شرعيه
I had a plan for my future. I wanted to go to college.
انا لدي خطه لمستقبلي. انا اريد ان اذهب للكليه.
I studied really hard in college,
انا درست بجد شديد في الكليه ,
and I was proud to be one of the very few female computer science graduates
وكنت متفائله بكوني واحده من خريجين علم الكمبيوتر النساء الاقلاء
at my university.
في كليتي
I wanted to have a career, so I went on to business school
انا اردت ان يكون لي مهنه , لذلك ذهبت لمدرسة التجاره
and I became one of the youngest female executives at Microsoft.
واصبحت واحده من اصغر المديرين التنفيذين النساء في Microsoft.
I still remember, though, when I left my parents' home
انا لا زلت اتذكر , رغم انه , عندما تركت بيت ابوي
to move across the country to start this new job at Microsoft.
للذهاب عبر المدينه لبدء عملي في Microsoft.
They had sacrificed a lot to give me five years of higher education.
انهم ضحو بالكثير لاعطائي خمس سنوات من التعليم العالي .
But they said, as I left home --
ولكنهم قالو ,وانا اترك المنزل --
and I literally went down the front steps, down the porch at home --
وذهبت حرفيا لاسف السلم الامامي اسفل الشرفه في المنزل --
and they said,
وقالو ,
"Even though you've had this great education,
"علي الرغم من انك قد تلقيت هذا التعليم العظيم ,
if you decide to get married and have kids right away,
لو قررتي الزواج وانجاب اطفال في الطريق الصحيح ,
that's OK by us, too."
انه جيد بالنسبه لنا , ايضا "
They wanted me to do the thing that would make me the very happiest.
انهم ارادوا ان افعل الشئ الذي سيجعلني سعيده جدا .
I was free to decide what that would be.
كنت حره لاختيار كيف يمكن ان يكون هذا .
It was an amazing feeling.
انه كان شعورا رائعا .
In fact, I did want to have kids --
في الحقيقة اردت ان انجب --
but I wanted to have them when I was ready.
ولكني اردت ان انجبهم عندما اكون مستعده .
And so now, Bill and I have three.
وكذلك الان , بيل وانا عندنا ثلاثه .
And when our eldest daughter was born,
وعندما ولدت ابنتنا الاكبر ,
we weren't, I would say, exactly sure how to be great parents.
لم نكن , انا يمكنني ان اقول متاكدين بالضبط كيف يكون الوالدين العظماء .
Maybe some of you know that feeling.
ممكن بعض منكم يعرف هذا الشعور .
And so we waited a little while before we had our second child.
و لذلك انتظرنا قليلا قبل ان ننجب ثاني طفل لنا .
And it's no accident that we have three children
وليس من قبيل الصدفه ان انجبنا علي ثلاثة اطفال
that are spaced three years apart.
كان هناك فرق ثلاثة سنوات .
Now, as a mother, what do I want the very most for my children?
الان ,كأم , ماذا اريد بشده لاطفالي ؟
I want them to feel the way I did --
انا اريدهم ان يشرعوا بما فعلت --
like they can do anything they want to do in life.
مثل انهم يمكنهم فعل اي شئ يريدونه في حياتهم.
And so, what has struck me
وهكذا , ما ادهشني
as I've travelled the last decade for the foundation around the world
اني سافرت العقد المضي حول العالم كله
is that all women want that same thing.
وهذا نفس الشئ الذي يريده الامهات لاولادهم.
Last year, I was in Nairobi, in the slums, in one called Korogocho --
السنه الماضيه , انا كنت في نيروبي, في الاحياء الفقيره, تحديدا كروجوتشو
which literally means when translated, "standing shoulder to shoulder."
الذي يعني حرفيا عندما يترجم , "الوقوف كتفا بكتف "
And I spoke with this women's group that's pictured here.
وتكلمت مع مجموعه من النساء المصورين هنا .
And the women talked very openly about their family life in the slums,
النساء تكلمت بتفتح عن عائللاتهم في العشوائيات ,
what it was like.
كان ذلك مثل كيف كانت تبدو.
And they talked quite intimately about what they did for birth control.
وتحدثوا بشكل وثيق عن ما علملو من اجل منع الحمل .
Marianne, in the center of the screen in the red sweater,
مارينا , في منتصف الشاشه مرتديه الرداء الاحمر ,
she summed up that entire two-hour conversation
لقد لخصت مفاد مناقشة ساعتين
in a phrase that I will never forget.
في جمله لم انساها ابدا .
She said, "I want to bring every good thing to this child
انها قالت " انا اريد انا احمل كل خير لهذا الطفل
before I have another."
قبل ان انجب الاخر ."
And I thought -- that's it.
وقد قالت -- هذا كل شئ
That's universal.
هذا هو العالم
We all want to bring every good thing to our children.
كلنا نريد ان نجلب الخير لاطفالنا.
But what's not universal is our ability to provide every good thing.
ولكن الغير عالمي هو قدرتنا علي توفير كل ما هو جيد .
So many women suffer from domestic violence.
كثير من النساء عانو من العنف المنزلي .
And they can't even broach the subject of contraception,
وم يكونو قادرين حتي ان يطرحو موضوع منع الحمل ,
even inside their own marriage.
حتي داخل زواجهم.
There are many women who lack basic education.
يوجد كثير من النساء الذين لم يتلقو التعليم الاساسي .
Even many of the women who do have knowledge and do have power
وحتي كثير من النساء الذين لديهم عندهم معرفة وقوة
don't have access to contraceptives.
لا يمكنهم الوصول لموانع الحمل .
For 250 years, parents around the world
لمدة 250 سنه , الوالدين حول العالم
have been deciding to have smaller families.
قرارو ان يحظوا بعائلة صغيره
This trend has been steady for a quarter of a millennium,
وكان هذا القرار ثابت لربع الفيه ,
across cultures and across geographies,
عبر الحضارات و المناطق الجغرافيه,
with the glaring exception of sub-Saharan Africa and South Asia.
مع استثناء صارخ من جنوب الصحراء الكبرى وجنوب آسيا
The French started bringing down their family size in the mid-1700s.
الفرنسيين بدأو تقليل حجم عائلاتهم في منتصف 1700
And over the next 150 years, this trend spread all across Europe.
وخلال 150 سنه انتشر هذا حول اوروبا كلها
The surprising thing to me, as I learned this history,
الشئ المفاجئ بالنسبه لي , كما درست التاريخ ,
was that it spread not along socioeconomic lines but around cultural lines.
كان انتشار ذلك ليس علي المستوي الاقتصادي او الاجتماعي بل المستوي الحضاري .
People who spoke the same language made that change as a group.
الناس الذين يتحدثون نفس اللغه احدثوا تغيرات كمجموعات .
They made the same choice for their family,
انهم صنعو نفس القرار لعائلاتهم ,
whether they were rich or whether they were poor.
سواء كانوا اغنيه ام فقراء .
The reason that trend toward smaller families spread
والسبب في الاتجاه نحوه العائلات الصغيره
was that this whole way was driven by an idea --
كان الطريق الجديد الذي تسوقه فكرة --
the idea that couples can exercise conscious control
الفكرة ان الازواج يمكنهم الممارسه مع مراقبه واعيه
over how many children they have.
علي عدد الاطفال المنجبين .
This is a very powerful idea.
الفكرة قويه .
It means that parents have the ability to affect the future,
انها تعني ان الاباء عندهم القدره علي التاثير علي المستقبل ,
not just accept it as it is.
ليس فقط الموافقه عليه كما هو .
In France, the average family size went down every decade
في فرنسا , معدل حجم الاسر يقل كل عقد
for 150 years in a row until it stabilized.
لمدة 150 عام حتي استقر .
It took so long back then because the contraceptives weren't that good.
استغرق الامر وقتا طويلا لان موانع الحمل لم تكن جيد .
In Germany, this transition started in the 1880s, and it took just 50 years
في المنيا ,التحول بدا في 1880, واخذ 50 سنه فقط
for family size to stabilize in this country.
لحجم الاسرة حتي الاسقرار في هذا البلد
And in Asia and Latin America, the transition started in the 1960s,
في اسيا وامريكا اللاتينيه التحول بدأ في 1960 ,
and it happened much faster because of modern contraception.
وحدث اسرع بسبب الموانع الحديثه .
I think, as we go through this history, it's important to pause for a moment
انا اعتقد , عندما نري التاريخ , هناك نقطه مهمه لنتوقف عندها للحظة
and to remember why this has become such a contentious issue.
وتذكر لماذا اصبح مثل هذه القضيه مثير للجدل .
It's because some family planning programs
انه بسبب بعض برامج تنظيم الاسرة
resorted to unfortunate incentives and coercive policies.
لجأت الحوافز المؤسفه والسياسات القهريه.
For instance, in the 1960s, India adopted very specific numeric targets
علي سبيل المثال , في 1960, الهند اعتمدت ارقام محدده جدا
and they paid women to accept having an IUD placed in their bodies.
و دفعوا للنساء لقبول الاجهاض .
Now, Indian women were really smart in this situation.
الان نساء الهند كانو حقيقتا اذكياء في هذه الحاله .
When they went to get an IUD inserted, they got paid six rupees.
عندما ذهبوا للحصول علي المال مقابل اللولب, وقد دفع لهم 6 روبيه .
And so what did they do?
ولكن ماذا فعلو بعدها ؟
They waited a few hours or a few days,
لقد انتظروا بعض ساعات او ايام ,
and they went to another service provider and had the IUD removed for one rupee.
و ذهبو لمقدم خدمه اخر وازالو اللولب بواحد روبيه .
For decades in the United States,
لعقود في الولايات المتحده ,
African-American women were sterilized without their consent.
النساء الافريقيات الامريكيات كانو يعقموا دون موافقتهم .
The procedure was so common
هذا الاجراء كان مشهور جدا
it became known as the Mississippi appendectomy --
انه اصبح معروف بأسم استأصال الزائده الدوديه --
a tragic chapter in my country's history.
فصل مأسوي في تاريخ بلادي .
And as recently as the 1990s, in Peru,
ومؤخرا تقريبا في 1990, في بيرو ,
women from the Andes region were given anesthesia
نساء منمنطقة جبال الانديز اعطيت تخدير
and they were sterilized without their knowledge.
وتم تعقيمهم دون علمهم .
The most startling thing about this
الشئ المفزع حول هذا
is that these coercive policies weren't even needed.
غير ان هذه السياسات القهريه لم تكن هناك حاجه لها .
They were carried out in places
وتنفذ في اماكن
where parents already wanted to lower their family size.
الاباء بالفعل ارادو تقليل حجم اسرهم .
Because in region after region, again and again,
لانه في منطقه بعد منطقة , مرارا وتكرارا
parents have wanted to have smaller families.
الوالدين يرويدون حجم اصغر لاسرهم .
There's no reason to believe
لا يجود سبب لتصديق
that African women have innately different desires.
ان النساء الافريقيات لدياها شهوة عاليه بالفطرة
Given the option, they will have fewer children.
اعطاء الاختيار , سيجعلهم ينجبوا اطفال اقل .
The question is:
السؤال هو :
will we invest in helping all women get what they want now?
هل سنستاهم في مساعدة النساء الذين يحتاجون المساعده الان ؟
Or, are we going to condemn them to some century-long struggle,
ام , اننا سنحاربهم طوال القرن ,
as if this was still revolutionary France
كما كانت ايام الثورة الفرنسيه
and the best method was coitus interruptus?
وافضل طريقة هي سحب القضيب قبل القذف ؟
Empowering parents -- it doesn't need justification.
تمكين الاهل -- لا يحتاج التبرير .
But here's the thing -- our desire to bring every good thing to our children
ولكن هناك شئ -- رغبتنا لجلب كل شئ جيد لاطفالنا
is a force for good throughout the world.
هي قوة للخير في العالم كله .
It's what propels societies forward.
وهو ما يدفع المجتمعات للامام
In that same slum in Nairobi, I met a young businesswoman,
في نفس الحي الفقير في نيروبي, قابلت سيدة اعمال صغيره ,
and she was making backpacks out of her home.
وكانت تصنع حقيبة ظهر خارج المنزل .
She and her young kids would go to the local jeans factory
هي واطفالها سيذهبوا لمصنع الجينز المحلي
and collect scraps of denim.
ويجمعوا القصاصات .
She'd create these backpacks and resell them.
وقالت انها تصنع حقائب ظهر وتبيعها .
And when I talked with her, she had three children,
وعندما تحدثت معها , بقد كان عندها ثلاثة اطفال ,
and I asked her about her family.
وسالتها عن عائلتها.
And she said she and her husband decided
وقالت هي وزوجها قرروا
that they wanted to stop having children after their third one.
التوقف عن الانجاب بعد طفلهم الثالث .
And so when I asked her why, she simply said,
ولذلك انا سالتها لماذا , هي قالت ببساطه ,
"Well, because I couldn't run my business if I had another child."
"لاني لا استطيع ان امارس عملي لو انجبت طفل اخر . "
And she explained the income that she was getting out of her business
وشرحت دخلها من عملها
afforded her to be able to give an education to all three of her children.
الذي وفر لها التعليم لابنائها الثلاثه .
She was incredibly optimistic about her family's future.
لقد كانت متفائله بشكل لا يصدق عن مستقبل عائلتها .
This is the same mental calculus
هذا هو الحساب العقلي
that hundreds of millions of men and women have gone through.
الذي حسبه مئات الملايين من الرجال والنساء .
And evidence proves that they have it exactly right.
والدليل يثبت انهم حسبوها صح
They are able to give their children more opportunities
انهم قادرين ان يعكوا اطفالهم فرص اكثر
by exercising control over when they have them.
بعمل نظام للوقت الذي ينجبوا فيه .
In Bangladesh,
في بنجلاديش ,
there's a district called Matlab.
هناك حي يسمي ماتلاب .
It's where researchers have collected data on over 180,000 inhabitants since 1963.
انه المكان الذي جمع فيه العلماء المعلومات علي حوالي 180,000 ساكن منذ عام 1963.
In the global health community,
في مجتمع الصحة العالمي ,
we like to say it's one of the longest pieces of research that's been running.
نحن نفضل ان نقول واحدا من اطول الاجزاء في البحث بداءت
We have so many great health statistics.
لدينا الكثير من الاحصاءات الصحيه العظيمه.
In one of the studies, what did they do?
في واحده من الدراسات , ماذا فعلوا ؟
Half the villagers were chosen to get contraceptives.
نصف القرويين اختيروا للحصول علي موانع الحمل .
They got education and access to contraception.
لقد حصلو علي تعليم والوصول لموانع الحمل .
Twenty years later, following those villages,
بعد 20 عاما , بتتبعنا لهذه القري ,
what we learned is that they had a better quality of life than their neighbors.
وجدنا انهم لديهم مستوي معيشي افضل من جيرانهم .
The families were healthier.
كانوا اكثر صحه .
The women were less likely to die in childbirth.
كانت نسبة الوفيات اثناء الولاده .
Their children were less likely to die in the first thirty days of life.
الوفيات في الشهر الاول للاطفال اقل .
The children were better nourished.
الاطفال كان غذائهم افضل .
The families were also wealthier.
العائلات كانت ايضا اغني .
The adult women's wages were higher.
وكانت اجور النساء اعلي .
Households had more assets -- things like livestock or land or savings.
الاسر لديها المزيد من الاصول -- مثل المواشي او الاراضي او المدخرات .
Finally, their sons and daughters had more schooling.
واخيرا, ابنائهم وبناتهم كانو اكثر ذهابا للمدرسه .
So when you multiply these types of effects over millions of families,
لذلك عندما تجمع هذه الصور من المعلومات علي مدار ملايين العائلات ,
the product can be large-scale economic development.
ويمكن للناتج ان يكون تطورا اقتصاديا .
People talk about the Asian economic miracle of the 1980s --
الناس تكلمو عن معجزة الاقتصاد الاسيوي عام 1980 تقريا --
but it wasn't really a miracle.
ولكنه في الحقيقه لم يكن معجزة .
One of the leading causes of economic growth across that region
واحده من الاسباب القياديه لنمو الاقتصاد علي هذا النطاق
was this cultural trend towards smaller families.
كان الاتجاه الثقافي الداعي لتصغير الاسر .
Sweeping changes start at the individual family level --
تغيرات شامله تبدا في مستوي الاسر الفرديه --
the family making a decision about what's best for their children.
الاسر تتخذ قرار ما هو الافضل لاطفالهم .
When they make that change and that decision,
عندما يحدثوا تغير ويتخذو ا هذا القرار
those become sweeping regional and national trends.
يحدثوا تغييركاسح للاتجاهات الاقليميه والوطنيه .
When families in sub-Saharan Africa are given the opportunity
عندما تعطي اسر جنوب الصحراء الكبري في افريقيا هذه الفرصه
to make those decisions for themselves,
لاتخاذ هذا القرار بنفسهم ,
I think it will help spark a virtuous cycle of development
انا اعتقد انها سوف تكون شرارة لدورة تنمية فعاله
in communities across the continent.
في المجتمعات في جميع القارات .
We can help poor families build a better future.
بامكاننا مساعدة الاسر الفقيرة لبناء مستقبل افضل .
We can insist that all people have the opportunity
بامكاننا ان نصر علي ان يحظا كل البشر بحق فرصة
to learn about contraceptives
العلم عن وسائل منع الحمل
and have access to the full variety of methods.
والقدره الكامله علي الوصول اليها .
I think the goal here is really clear:
اعتقد ان الهدف هنا واضح :
universal access to birth control that women want.
وصول العالم كله لموانع الحمل عندما تحتاجه النساء .
And for that to happen, it means that both rich and poor governments alike
وليحدث هذها , يجب ان كلا من الحكومات الغنيه والفقيره
must make contraception a total priority.
تضع موانع الحمل من اولوياتها .
We can do our part, in this room and globally,
يمكننا ان نأدي جزئنا , من هذه الغرفه وعالمين ,
by talking about the hundreds of millions of families
بالتحدث مع مئات الملايين من العائلات
that don't have access to contraception today
الذين لايستطيعوا الوصول الي موانع الحمل اليوم
and what it would do to change their lives if they did have access.
وكيف سيغير هذا حياتهم لو استطاعوا الوصول له .
I think if Marianne and the members of her women's group
انا اعتقد مارينا واعضاء فريقها
can talk about this openly
يمكنهم التحدث عن هذا
and have this discussion out amongst themselves and in public,
ويكون هذا النقاش بينهم وعلي الملأ,
we can, too.
يمكننا , ايضا .
And we need to start now.
ونحتاج ان نبدا الان .
Because like Marianne, we all want to bring every good thing to our children.
لانه مثل مارينا , نحن كلنا نريد ان نأتي بكل شئ جيد لاطفالنا .
And where is the controversy in that?
واين الجدال في هذا ؟
Thank you.
شكرا .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Thank you.
كريس اندرسون: شكرا لكم .
I have some questions for Melinda.
انا عندي بعض الاسئله لميلندا .
(Applause ends)
(التصفيق انتهي)
Thank you for your courage and everything else.
شكرا علي شجاعتك وكل شئ اخر .
So, Melinda, in the last few years
في السنوات الاخيره يا مليندا
I've heard a lot of smart people say something to the effect of,
انا سمعت عن اشخاص اذكياء كثيرا تقول شيئا للتاثير ,
"We don't need to worry about the population issue anymore.
"نحن لا نحتاج للاهتمام بمشكلة عدد السكان ثانيتا .
Family sizes are coming down naturally all over the world.
حجم العائلات يقل طبيعيا في العالم كله .
We're going to peak at nine or 10 billion. And that's it."
ونحن في طريقنا للقمه في 9-10 مليار , فقط "
Are they wrong?
هل هم خاطئين ؟
Melinda Gates: If you look at the statistics across Africa,
مليندا جايتس : لو قرأت الاحصائات حول افريقيا ,
they are wrong.
انهم خاطئيين .
And I think we need to look at it, though, from a different lens.
وانا اعتقد اننا يجب ان ننظر الي هذا بطريقة مختلفة
We need to look at it from the ground upwards.
نحن نحتاج ان نري هذا من اعلي السطح
I think that's one of the reasons we got ourselves in so much trouble
اعتقد ان هذا واحد من الاسباب التي تجعلنا نضع نفسنا في مشكله كبيرة
on this issue of contraception.
مع هذا العدد من وسائل منع الحمل
We looked at it from top down
لقد نظرنا له من اعلي لاسفل
and said we want to have different population numbers over time.
وقلنا اننا نريد تغير اعاد السكان م الوقت .
Yes, we care about the planet. Yes, we need to make the right choices.
نعم , اهتممنا بالكوكب نعم , نحتاج ان نتخذ الاختيار الصحيح .
But the choices have to be made at the family level.
ولكن الاختيارات تصنع علي مستوي العائلات .
And it's only by giving people access and letting them choose what to do
و هذا يختار فقط عند السماح للناس بالوصول والاختيار عن ماذا يريدون ان يفعلو
that you get those sweeping changes that we have seen globally --
هذا سيأتي بالتغيرات الكاسحه التي تراها في المجتمع --
except for sub-Saharan Africa and those places in South Asia and Afghanistan.
ماعدا جنوب الصحراء الكبري في افريقياوهؤلاء في جنوب اسيا وافغانستان .
CA: Some people on the right in America
CA : هناك ناس في امريكا علي حق
and in many conservative cultures around the world
والعديد من الثقافات المحافظة حول العالم
might say something like this:
ممكن تقول شيئا مثل ,
"It's all very well to talk about saving lives and empowering women and so on.
"انه جيد جدا عن التحدث عن الحياه وتقوية المرأه وهكذا .
But, sex is sacred.
ولكن , الجنس مقدس
What you're proposing is going to increase the likelihood
ما كنت اقول انه سيزيد من احتمال
that lots of sex happens outside marriage.
حدوث الكثير من الجنس خارج اطار الزواج
And that is wrong."
وهذا خطأ . "
What would you say to them?
ماذا تقولين لهم ؟
MG: I would say that sex is absolutely sacred.
MG : انا اريد ان اقول ان الجنس مقدس تماما .
And it's sacred in Germany, and it's sacred in the United States,
ومقدس في المانيا , والولايات المتحده ,
and it's sacred in France and so many places around the world.
ومقدس في فرنسا وكذلك العديد من الاماكن في العالم
And the fact that 98 percent of women in my country who are sexually experienced
في الحقيقه 98 % من النساء في بلدي لديهم خبره جسنيه
say they use birth control doesn't make sex any less sacred.
يقولون انهم يستخدمون موانع الحمل .
It just means that they're getting to make choices about their lives.
انه فقط يعني انهم يتخذون قرارات في حياتهم .
And I think in that choice,
انا اعتقد في هذا الاختيار,
we're also honoring the sacredness of the family
نحن نحترم ايضا قدسية الاسره
and the sacredness of the mother's life
وقدسية الام
and the childrens' lives by saving their lives.
وحياة الاطفال بحفظ حياتهم .
To me, that's incredibly sacred, too.
لشخصي , هذا مقدس بشكل لا يصدق ,ايضا .
CA: So what is your foundation doing to promote this issue?
CA:ما هو الاساس الخاص بك الذي تدعمي بيه هذه القضيه ؟
And what could people here and people listening on the web --
وماذا يمكن ان يفعل المستمعين هنا وعلي الانترنت --
what would you like them to do?
وماذا تريدي منهم ان يفعلو ؟
MG: I would say this -- join the conversation.
MG:اناوددت ان اقول هذا-- ان يشتركوا في النقاش.
We've listed the website up here. Join the conversation.
لقد سردت مواقع هنا . اشتركوا في النقاش.
Tell your story about how contraception has either changed your life
قولوا قصة تغير موانع الحمل لحياتكم
or somebody's life that you know.
او لحياة شخص تعرفونه .
And say that you're for this.
وقول اني لهاذا
We need a groundswell of people saying, "This makes sense.
نحن نحتاج الي اطياف عديده من البشر تقول , "الامرمعقول .
We've got to give all women access -- no matter where they live."
نحنعلينا ان نتيح لكل النساء -- لا يهم ان يعيشوا ."
And one of the things that we're going to do
وواحدا من الاشي اء التي سوف نصنعها
is do a large event July 11 in London,
هي اقامة حدث كبير في 11 يوليو,
with a whole host of countries, a whole host of African nations,
مع كل الدول المنظمة , وكل الدول الافريقية المنظمة,
to all say we're putting this back on the global health agenda.
لنقول للجمع ان نضع هذه مجددا علي جدول اعمال الصحه العالميه .
We're going to commit resources to it,
ونحن في طريقنا لتخصيص موارد لذلك ,
and we're going to do planning from the bottom up with governments
ونحن نخطط تصاعديا مع الحكومات
to make sure that women are educated --
لنتأكد ان النساء قد تعلموا --
so that if they want the tool, they have it,
بحيث اذا كانو يحتاجون هذه الاداة , يحصلوا عليها
and that they have lots of options available
ويكون لديهم عدة اختيارات ممكنه
either through their local healthcare worker
اما من خلال عمال الرعايه الصحيه المدنيه
or their local community rural clinic.
او العيادات الريفيه للمجتمع المحلي
CA: Melinda, I'm guessing that some of those nuns who taught you at school
CA:مليندا اعتقد ان بعض من الراهبات الذين علموكي في المدرسه
are going to see this TED Talk at some point.
سيشاهدوا هذا الحديث في وقت ما .
Are they going to be horrified, or are they cheering you on?
هل هم سيفزعوا , ام انهم سيشجعوك ؟
MG: I know they're going to see the TED Talk
MG : انا اعلم انهم سيروا هذا الحديث
because they know that I'm doing it and I plan to send it to them.
لانهم يعرفون اني افعل هذا واخطط اني سارسله لهم .
And, you know, the nuns who taught me were incredibly progressive.
و , انت تعلم , الراهبات الذين علموني كانت تقدميه شكل لا يصدق .
I hope that they'll be very proud of me
انا امل انهم سيكونون فخورين بي
for living out what they taught us about social justice and service.
للعيش خارج ما علمونا عن العداله الاجتماعيه والخدميه .
I have come to feel incredibly passionate about this issue
انا يجب ان احس عاطفيا بشكل لا يصدق حول هذه المسألة
because of what I've seen in the developing world.
لان ما رأيته في العالم النامي .
And for me, this topic has become very close to heart
وبالنسبة لي , هذا الموضوع قريب جدا لقلب
because you meet these women and they are so often voiceless.
لانك قابلت هذه النساء و في كثير من الاحيان هم صامتون .
And yet they shouldn't be --
وينبغي الا يكونو صامتين --
they should have a voice, they should have access.
يجب ان يكون لهم صوت , يجب ان يكون لهم حرية الوصول .
And so I hope they'll feel
ولذلك انا امل يحسوا
that I'm living out what I've learned from them
هذا ما عايش من ما تعلمت منهم
and from the decades of work that I've already done at the foundation.
ومن عقود من العمل انا فعلت ذلك اساسا.
CA: So, you and your team brought together today an amazing group of speakers
CA: انت و فريقك جمعتوا اليوم مجموعه مذهله من المتحدثين
to whom we're all grateful.
لذلك نحن جميعا ممتنون .
Did you learn anything?
هل تعلمت شئ ؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
MG: Oh my gosh, I learned so many things. I have so many follow-up questions.
MG: يا الهي , لقد تعلمت العديد من الاشياء. لدي الكثير من الاسئله المتابعه.
And I think a lot of this work is a journey.
واعتقد ان كثير من هذا العمل كان رحله .
You heard the discussion about the journey through energy,
هل سمعت المناقشه عن رحلة الطاقه,
or the journey through social design,
او الرحله خلال التصميم الاجتماعي ,
or the journey in the coming and saying,
او الرحله خلال القدوم و قولة ,
"Why aren't there any women on this platform?"
"لماذا لا توجد امرأة في هذا النظام ؟ "
And I think for all of us who work on these development issues,
واعقد هذا لنا جميعا العاملين علي تنمية هذه المشاكل ,
you learn by talking to other people.
انتم تتعلمون بالتحدث مع الناس الاخرين
You learn by doing. You learn by trying and making mistakes.
انت تتعلم بالفعل . انت تتعلم بالمحاولة والاخطاء ,
And it's the questions you ask.
وهذا هو السؤال الذي سالته .
Sometimes it's the questions you ask that helps lead to the answer
بعض الاحيان السؤال الذي سالت يساعد علي الوصول للاجابه
the next person that can help you answer it.
الشخص التالي الذي يمكن ان يساعدك لتجاوب هذا.
So I have lots of questions for the panelists from today.
لذلك ليس لدي كثير من الاسئله لاعضاء الفريق اليوم .
And I thought it was just an amazing day.
وظننتاعتقد انه كان يوم مدهش فقط .
CA: Melinda, thank you for inviting all of us on this journey with you.
CA: مادلينا , شكرا لدعوتك لنا جميعا لهذه الرحله معك .
Thank you so much. MG: Great. Thanks, Chris.
شكرا جدا MG : عظيم . شكرا , كريس